A Guide to the Hubard Family Papers 1749-1950
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Guide to the Hubard Family Papers 1749-1950
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8039, 8039-a, 8039-b
This collection consists of 12 shelf feet of items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The original collection was a 1965 loan of Robert T. Hubard Jr. (IV) of Hampden-Sydnye, Va. On May 14, 1974, Mr. Hubard made a gift of the original collection (8039) to the University of Virginia together with two groups of additional materials (8039-a, 8039-b), which are interfiled in the original collection. On the same date Mr. Hubard gave his literary rights to the collection to the University of Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
The Hubard Family Papers, ca. 1749(1845-1930)1950, consist of 12 shelf feet of chiefly correspondence, legal documents, bills and receipts, account books and printed material os the first, second, and third Robert T. Hubards.
Robert Thruston Hubard I (1808-1871), who was educated at Hampden-Sydney and the University of Virginia, was a planter at Rosney in Buckingham County and after 1850, at Chellowe, which he purchased from his brother-in-law, Robert Bolling. Hubard's wife, formerly Susan Pocahantas Bolling, was seventh in descent from John Rolfe's marriage to Pocahantas through a granddaughter, Jane Rolfe, who married Colonel Robert Bolling in 1675. This ancestry is represented in the collection by ca. 50 pages of genealogical material. Of interest in the correspondence are letters to Hubard from his brothers William Bolling Hubard and Edmund Wilcox Hubard, a member of the U.S. House of Representatives from 1841-1847, touching on political issues of the period, and ca. 30 letters, 1851-1857, from Hubard's son, James L., relating his experiences as a cadet at Virginia Military Institute. Also included are a letter from Philip St. George Cocke concerning James Linneaus Hubard's appointment to VMI, an extensive 1840 letter from Buchner Thruston re: Hubard family history and numerous letters concerning plantation business. Other Robert Thruston Hubard I material of note are his plantation journals, 1847-1871, and his lecture notes for Professor Tucker's economics class at the University of Virginia in 1828.
Robert Thruston Hubard II (1839-1921) after attending Hampden-Sydney College and the University of Virginia Law School, practiced law for several years in Richmond before returning to Chellowe in 1887, practicing law thereafter in Buckingham, Cumberland, and Prince Edward Counties. Among the legal papers in the collection are ca. 40 documents of the Orange- Keysville Railway, of which Hubard was president. The majority of the correspondence to and from him concerns the legal cases that he handled. Included are letters from members of the Tucker family re: the family estate, letters from H.C Cabell and H.P. Randolph as well as several letters from Thomas Staples Martin relating to a legal case. Of special note among the correspondence are a letter from Horace Greeley dated May 30, 1872 concerning the sending of a delegation to the Democratic National Convention in Baltimore, a letter from George C. Cabell to President-Elect McKinley recommending that Hubard be appointed First Assistant to the U.S. Attorney General, and a letter from Governor William Smith commending Robert T. Hubard II for his work in the Virginia Legislature, 1875-1877.
During the Civil War, Robert T. Hubard was a Lieutenant-Colonel in the Third Virginia Cavalry, during which time he wrote several letters containing accounts of battles in which he participated. And in a June 5, 1910 letter to his son, he recounts the battle of May 8, 1864, on the Brock road near Spottsylvania Courthouse.
Also among the correspondence are copies of letters dating 1835-1842 from John R. Edmunds, Hubard's father-in-law, to Walter C. Coles, a member of the U.S. Congress. In these letters Edmunds discusses political issues of the period, e.g. abolitionism, the U.S. Treasury, and economic policy. In addition the collection contains ca. 70 pages of genealogical material and history of the Edmunds family.
Robert Thruston Hubard III (1876- ) was educated at Hampden-Sydney College, as was his father, and the University of Virginia Law School, after which he practiced law in Fayetteville, West Virginia. He married Ruth Drewry Whittle, daughter of Judge Stafford G. Whittle of Martinsville, Va., after a courtship in which they exchanged numerous letters amounting to 2 shelf feet along with those written during their marriage.
Among the general material of the colelction are several items concerning slavery, such as a list of Robert T. Hubard I's slaves and their value at the time of emancipation, a list of Virginia counties having fewer than 500 taxable slaves and a table of the population, both slave and white, of Virginia by decades from 1790-1840.
Organization
The collection is divided into four major sections in the following order: 1) correspondence, 2) legal documents and memoranda, 3) bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts, 4) general material. In each of sections 1-3 the material is arranged chronologically. The material of section 4 is grouped topically in descending order of importance.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1781-1951
  - [Robert] Lawson to Major William Hubbard 1781 April 21, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1828, 1836-1844, 17 items (Box 1)
  - Copies of letters from John R. Edmunds to Walter Coles 1835-1842, 7 items (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1847-1863, 1865, 175 items, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1866-1877, 316 items, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1878-1889, 320 items, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1890-1909, 220 items, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1910 Jan-Oct, 164 items, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1910 Nov-1911 March, 172 items, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1911 April-Dec, 184 items, 9 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1912 Jan-July, 171 items, 8 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1912 Aug-Sept 11, 50 items, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Correspondence 1913 Jan-1914 April, 116 items, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Correspondence 1914 May-1919, 204 items, 8 folders (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1920, 47 items (Box 11)
  - Letters of condolence to Robert T. Hubard III on the death of his wife ca. 1290 Feb 26-March, 75 items (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1921, 25 items (Box 11)
  - Correspondence from Hubard children 1921-1924, 35 items (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1922-1924, 148 items, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1925-1930, 100 items, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Correspondence 1937-1938, 39 items, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Correspondence 1940-1951, 14 items (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 108 items, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Carbons of business letters of Robert T. Hubard III 1903 May 15-1904 Oct, 1 vol. (Box 13)
  - Carbons of business letters of Rober T. Hubard III 1904 Nov.-1905 May 11, 1 vol. (Box 13)
- Legal Documents and Memoranda 1749-1923
  - Copy of a royal land grant to John Hughes 1749 (1908), 1 item (Box 14)
  - Copy of land grant to Henry Baird 1762 (1913), 1 item (Box 14)
  - Statement of insturctions to delegates Thomas Read and Wm. Hubard from the Freeholders of Charlotte Co. and newspaper article re: same 1176 Oct 16 and 1907 May 28, 2 items (Box 14)
  - Copy of land grant to Henry Wooldridge 1796 (1913), 1 item (Box 14)
  - Copy of land grant to John Patterson 1804 (1913), 1 item (Box 14)
  - Legal documents re: Peyton Lesueur 1827, 4 items (Box 14)
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1833-1848, 12 items (Box 14)
  - Legal documents and memoranda ca. 1850-1859, 12 items (Box 14)
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1852-1875, 20 items (Box 14)
    re: Robert Bolling's debt to Robert Thruston Hubard
  - Will and directions to Robert Thruston Hubard's children ca. 1855-1871, 7 items (Box 14)
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1861-1878, 17 items (Box 14)
    re: Robert Thruston Hubard estate
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1867-1881, 45 items (Box 14)
    re: Samuel Williams
  - Legal documents and memoranda ca. 1870-1874, 27 items (Box 14)
  - Legal documents and memoranda ca. 1870-1877, 11 items (Box 14)
    re: Judith Randolph estate
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1871-1896, 18 items (Box 14)
    re: Anna D. Randolph estate
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1872-1877, 5 items (Box 14)
    re: Garnett and Moseley Gold Mining Co.
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1875-1877, 33 items (Box 14)
  - Legal documents and memoranda ca. 1876-1880, 4 items (Box 14)
    re: D.C. Randolph bankruptcy
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1878-1879, 46 items (Box 14)
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1878-1883, 15 items (Box 15)
    re: Magdalene Maupin estate
  - Legal documents and memoranda ca. 1878-1885, 18 items (Box 15)
    re: John St. George Randolph estate
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1879-1880, 4 items (Box 15)
    re: George Fulcher estate
  - Legal documents and records ca. 1800-1885, 7 items (Box 15)
    re: claims against French Government by Edmunds family
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1880-1889, 50 items (Box 15)
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1887-1915, 40 items (Box 15)
    re: Orange-Keysville Railway
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1890-1989, 8 items (Box 15)
  - Legal documents and memoranda 1902-1923, 8 items (Box 15)
  - Legal documents and memoranda, 33 items (Box 15)
- Bills, Receipts, Promissory Notes, and Accounts 1829-1959
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1829-1839, 11 items (Box 16)
  - Receipts for grain received at Tye River Warehouse 1839-1841, 1848-1849, 50 items (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1840-1849, 35 items (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1842 April 27, 1 item (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1850-1959, 50 items (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1853-1859, 100 items (Box 16)
    re: John H. Miller
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1856-1862, 26 items (Box 16)
    re: Alex Moseley trust fund
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1860-1868, 60 items (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1860-1879, 30 items (Box 16)
    re: Samuel Williams Estate
  - Receipts re: special election for Farmville and Charlottesville Railroad Co. 1862, 4 items (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1868-1879, 250 items (Box 16)
    re: Robert Thruston Hubard, Sr. estate
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1869, 50 items (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1869-1870, 20 items (Box 16)
    re: Robert Thruston Hubard, Jr's guardianship of Anna T. Daniels
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1869-1885, 25 items (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1870-1871, 100 items (Box 16)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1870-1879, 75 items (Box 16)
    re: Robert Bolling
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1870-1879, 100 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1870-1885, 30 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1872, 50 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1872-1896, 125 items (Box 17)
    re: Anna Daniel Randolph estate
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1873, 75 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1873-1915, 25 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1874, 150 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1874-1875, 10 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1875, 200 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1875-1876, 50 items (Box 17)
    Robert T. Hubard with Harrison Hubard and Tom Allen
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1976, 200 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1876, 40 items (Box 18)
    of Robert Thruston Hubard, Jr. from Richmond
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1877, 200 items (Box 18)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1877 (Box 18)
    re: Brooke vs. Randolph
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1878, 100 items (Box 18)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1878-1881, 6 items (Box 18)
    re: J. St. George Randolph estate
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1879, 75 items (Box 18)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1879, 200 items (Box 18)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1880, 100 items (Box 18)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1880-1889, 100 items (Box 17)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1880-1889, 50 items (Box 19)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1881, 300 items (Box 19)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1882, 200 items, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1883, 100 items (Box 19)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1883-1884, 200 items (Box 19)
    City of Richmond Republican Executive Committee
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1884, 100 items (Box 19)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1885, 50 items (Box 19)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1886, 175 items (Box 20)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1887, 125 items (Box 20)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts 1888-1889, 20 items (Box 20)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1890-1899, 40 items (Box 20)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts ca. 1900-1949, 75 items (Box 20)
  - Bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounts, 70 items (Box 20)
  - Checkbook records ca. 1873-1894, 18 items (Box 20)
- General Material 1791-1940
  - List of slaves of Robert Thruston Hubard and their value at time of emancipation 1869 Oct. 25, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Population of Va., decades from 1790-1840, slave and white, 1 item (Box 21)
  - List of counties in Va. having fewer than 500 taxable slaves, 1 item (Box 21)
  - General order No. 9, Robert E. Lee, and quotations of Lee ca. 1865, 2 items (Box 21)
  - Oath of allegiance to U.S. of Robert Thruston Hubard, Jr. 1865 July 24, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Election results from Buckingham County for House of Delegates and for Hubard's race for Commonwealth Attorney, 2 items (Box 21)
  - Petition to Wm. McKinley, President-Elect, requesting that Robert Thruston Hubard, Jr. be made 1st Asst to the Attorney General 1897 Feb 3, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Outline of plan of organization of Republican Party, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Notes on the manner of election of state governors, 3 1. 1850, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Essay - Congressional Apportionment and Mr. President, 2 items (Box 21)
  - Essay - Reminiscences of Massachusetts and list of number of representatives in Congress from slaveholding states from 1798-1840, 2 items (Box 21)
  - To the Editors of the Richmond Whig re: the reannexation of Texas, 15 1. 1844, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Speeches of Robert Thruston Hubard, Jr., 4 items (Box 21)
  - Advice and family history written by Robert Thruston Hubard for his sons, 4 items (Box 21)
  - Certificate certifying that Robert Thruston Hubard meets requirements for law license 1931 July 11, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Robert Thruston Hubard, III's applications for law license 1894, 1902, 2 items (Box 21)
  - Letters of recommendation for Robert Thruston Hubard, III 1897-1901, 23 items (Box 21)
  - MOnthly grade reports of Robert Thruston Hubard, Jr. from Hampden-Sydney College, Lists of distinction 1892, 1894, 30 items (Box 21)
  - Maps of plots of land ca. 1791-1912, 14 items (Box 21)
  - Fragments of land survery, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Fragments of surveys of Rosney and Laeneus Bolling Plot 1836, n.d., 2 items (Box 21)
  - Weekly newsletter and Price Current - Petersburg and Merchants' Prices-Current and Shipping List 1853, 1854, 2 items (Box 21)
  - Schedule of price of gold during Civil War compared with Confederate money ca. 1865, 2 items (Box 21)
  - Stamp duties imposed by act of June 28, 1864 1866, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Life Insurance Policy of Thomas Leitsch and related receipts, and memorandum of policies filed by Robert Thruston Hubard 1868-1884, 7 items (Box 21)
  - Sketch of Chellowe with notes by Robert Thruston Hubard, Jr 1868, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Sketch of the life of Robert Thruston Hubard, Jr., 1 item (Box 21)
  - Genealogical material re: Bolling-Rolfe ancestry, 1 item, 54 p. (Box 21)
  - Geneaological material and family history re: Edmunds family, 70 1., 1 item (Box 21)
  - List of Bolling Hubard's books, 1 item (Box 21)
  - List of Bolling Hubard's books, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Medical prescription 1837 April 24, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Directions for making whitewash 1855, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Book on wine growing and fermenting, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Confederate bonds of Robert Thruston Hubard 1864, 4 items (Box 22)
  - Stocks and bonds 1842-1913, 32 items (Box 22)
  - Map of Washington, DC 1889, 1 item (Box 22)
  - Theatre posters 1867, 1881, 4 items (Box 22)
  - Auction sale bills 1875-1883, 7 items (Box 22)
  - Newspaper clippings ca. 1915, 4 items (Box 22)
    re: deaths of Mr. and Mrs. H.M. Drewry and Capt. C.W. Whittle
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings ca. 1870-1910, 50 items (Box 22)
  - Newspaper clippings 1920, 21 items (Box 22)
    re: death of Mrs. R. T. Hubard, III
  - Photographs, 9 items (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous invitations ca. 1860-1852, 27 items (Box 22)
  - Postcards and greeting cards ca. 1900-1940, 43 items (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous ca. 1850-1930, 150 items, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Daily Dispatch, Richmond, Va. 1879 Jan 1, 1 item (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous newspapers 1812, 1870, 1873, and 1928, 6 items (Box 23)
  - Catalog of Smithfield Male and Female Institute and related printed material 1901-1902, 4 items (Box 23)
  - Speeches, Congressional Bills, Court decisions and miscellaneous ca. 1825-1921, 37 items (Box 23)
  - Geography Text Book 1820, 1 item (Box 24)
  - Notes of Professor Tucker's lectures on economics at the University of Virginia by Robert Thruston Hubard 1828, 1 item (Box 24)
  - Memorandum of the Special Commissioner 1855, 1 item (Box 24)
  - Plantation journal of annual receipts and disbursements, Robert Thruston Hubard 1855-1871, 1 item (Box 24)
  - Plantation journal of annual receipts and disbursements, Robert Thruston Hubard 1847-1854, 1 item (Box 24)
  - Notes on family history by Robert Thruston Hubard 1858 June, 1 item (Box 24)
  - Plantation ledger of accounts of hands employed by Robert Thruston Hubard 1869, 1 item (Box 24)
  - Farm book for Chellowe 1869-1871, 1 item (Box 24)
  - Map of Mark Anthony lands by T.S. Robison 1884, 1 item